Guide to the George Eliot and George Henry Lewes Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Section III. Letters to/about GEORGE ELIOT & GEORGE HENRY LEWES
  - Ward, Elizabeth Stuart (Phelps), (Mrs. H.D. Ward)
    - Accompanied by a copy of selected passages from a letter from GE to E.S. Phelps, sent to GE to be copied by her after the original was acci- dentally destroyed., [July?] 1875. (Box 13)
  - Watson, Agnes C.
    - to GE, 1879 Mar 28 (Box 14)
    - ----, 1879 Sep 28 (Box 14)
  - Watt, A.S.
    - to Ellis & Ellis, 1926 Mar 4 (Box 14)
  - Watts, George Frederic, 1818-1904
    - to GE, 1870 Jan 12 (Box 14)
  - Wedgwood, Frances Julia
    - to GE, 1872 Nov 8 (Box 14)
    - to Barbara Bodichon, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Wheatley, Henry Benjamin, 1838-1919
    - List of articles on the age of the earth prepared for GE at the request of Warren De la Rue., [1878] (Box 14)
  - White, Edgar
    - to GE, 1874 Jul 25 (Box 14)
  - White, Newman Ivy
    - to C. L. Lewes, 1936 Aug 20 (Box 14)
  - Williams, J.E.
    - to GE, 1871 Dec 9 (Box 14)
  - Williams, Samuel D., Jr.
    - to GE, No year May 9 (Box 14)
    - ----, [1878 Dec 2] (Box 14)
    - to GHL, 1865 Sep 15 (Box 14)
  - Willim, Elizabeth (Ashweek) Lewes, (Mrs. John G. Willim, GHL's mother), 1787-1870
    - to GHL, [1860] (Box 14)
  - Wills, William Gorman, 1828-1891
    - with draft of reply by C.L. Lewes on verso, [1879?] (Box 14)
  - Wilson, William James Erasmus, 1809-1884
    - to GE, 1878 Dec 10 (Box 14)
  - Winkworth, Emma
    - to GE, 1873 Dec 4 (Box 14)
    - to Mrs. Edmund, 1873 Jan 15 (Box 14)
  - Winkworth, Susanna, 1820-1884
    - to GE, 1859 Apr 7 (Box 14)
  - Withers, Edmund
    - to GHL, 1859 May 17 (Box 14)
  - Wood, William
    - to J.W. Cross, 1878 Nov 8
      - ----, 1878 Dec 31 (Box 14)
      - ----, 1885 Feb 10 (Box 14)
      - ----, 1885 Mar 10 (Box 14)
      - incomplete, n.d. (Box 14)
    - to GE, 1877 Feb 27 (Box 14)
  - Yeo, Gerald Francis, 1845-1909
    - On behalf of the Physiological Society, 1878 Dec 17 (Box 14)
  - Young, Henry, & Sons, Ltd.
    - to Gertrude (Hill) Lewes, 1922 Jul 28 (Box 14)
- Section IV. George Eliot. WRITINGS, 1854-1861
  - 1. JOURNAL, 1854-1861 (Box 15)
    Contains recollections of Weimar (1854), Berlin (1854-55), Ilfracombe (1856), the Scilly Isles (1857), Jersey (1857); "How I came to write Fiction"; and the "History of Adam Bede." 152 leaves 21 cm. Accompanied by typescript prepared by Richard L. Purdy.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Sold by Miss Elsie Druce, niece of J. W. Cross, at Sotheby's on 17 April 1930, item 911. Purchased with the Altschul Fund, 1931.
  - 2. JOURNAL, 1858-1860 (Box 16)
    Contains journal of a trip to Germany, April 14-October 27, 1858 and beginning at the back of the book, "Recollections of Italy, 1860." 175 p. Accompanied by typescript prepared by Richard L. Purdy.
    Sold by Miss Elsie Druce, niece of J. W. Cross, at Sotheby's on 17 April 1930, item 915. Purchased with the Altschul Fund.
  - 3. JOURNAL, 1861-77 Jul-Dec (Box 17)
    "Order of writings", a list of GE's works up to 1876, precedes the first page of the diary. 144 p. [53 blank] 15 cm. Accompanied by typescript prepared by Richard L. Purdy.
    Gift of Chauncey B. Tinker, 1955.
    Tinker 868
  - 4. JOURNAL, 1864-1865 (Box 18)
    Contains journal of a trip to Italy in 1864 and to Normandy in 1865. 137 p. [74 blank] 12 cm. Accompanied by typescript prepared by Richard L. Purdy.
    Tinker 869
  - 5. DIARY, 1880 Jan 1-Dec 4 (Box 19)
    Contains also cash accounts for the year 1880. Accompanied by typescript prepared by Richard L. Purdy.
    Purchased from Gabriel Wells with the Library Associates Fund, 1935.
  - 6. COMMONPLACE NOTEBOOK, with index. 307 p. (Box 20)
    Sold by Miss Elsie Druce, niece of J.W. Cross, at Sotheby's on 17 April 1930, item 913. Purchased with the Altschul Fund, 1931.
  - 7. NOTEBOOK, copied about 1873-1876 (Box 21)
    Contains poetry and prose including In a London Drawing room; Ex Oriente Lux; Arms! To Arms!; In the South; Erinna; The Death of Moses; Mottoes (Felix Holt); Notes on Form in Art; Versification. The dates at the end of the poems (1865-1869) indicate probable dates of composition. 73 leaves [31 blank and 3 cut out].
    Purchased from Gabriel Wells with the A. H. Childs Fund. 1950.
  - 8. NOTEBOOK, 1880 (Box 22)
    Contains miscellaneous notes and quotations, some in Greek and German. 20 p. 11 cm.
    Sold by Miss Elsie Druce, niece of J.W. Cross, at Sotheby's on 9 April 1935, item 435. Gift of Chauncey B. Tinker, 1955. Tinker 867
  - 9. NOTES, 1876 (Box 23)
    Notes, possibly for a projected novel, on the back of a card calendar for January 1876. 1 card. 9.5 x 13.5 cm.
    Purchased from C.A. Stonehill with the Library Associates Fund, 1944. Published in Blanche Colton Williams' George Eliot, a biography, New York, Macmillan, 1936. p. 290-291.
  - 10. NOTEBOOK, [1861] (Box 24)
    Notebook of memoranda, statistics, historical notes and quotations collected in preparation for writing Felix Holt, The Spanish Gypsy. 150 p. 14 cm.
    Tinker 866
  - 11. ETHICA, [1855] (Box 25)
    GE's translation of Spinoza's Ethica, parts 1-5. 654 leaves 23 cm. Accompanied by GHL's "Notes and additions to the Theologico-Political Tractate " of Spinoza. 9 leaves.
    Purchased from Mrs. Elinor Ouvry with the Library Associates Fund, 1942.
  - 12. ADDRESS BOOK (Box 26)
    Notebook with addresses in the hands of GE and GHL. 64 leaves 14.5 cm.
    Purchased from C. A. Stonehill with the Library Associates Fund, 1944.
  - 13. SCHOOL NOTEBOOK, 1834 (Box 27)
    This notebook, the earliest known GE manuscript, contains poems copied from various sources, rules and illustrative problems in arithmetic, an essay on "Affectation and Conceit," and a story, "Edward Neville." 66 leaves.
    Purchased from J. H. P. Pafford with the Library Associates Fund.
  - 14. "BROTHER JACOB", [1860] (Box 28)
    A short story published in the Cornhill Magazine, July 1864, and a poem, "A College Breakfast Party," April 1874, published in Macmillan's Magazine, July 1878. 128 leaves, probably bound by C.L. Lewes, 1881.
    Purchased from Mrs. Ouvry with the Library Associates Fund.
  - 15. MEMORANDUM by GE, [February 1862] (Box 29)
    Of the agreement with Smith, Elder & Co. relating to the copyright of Romola. With note on verso by Mrs. Ouvry.
  - 16. "ZODAICAL ASPECTS", 1868 (Box 30)
    4 p. removed from one of the notebooks for The Spanish Gypsy, 1868. Removed from v. 25 of GE's Works, Boston, 1908.
  - 17. "TWO LOVERS" (Box 31)
    A poem. Two versions. First version dated March 1865. 1 p. 23 cm. Second version dated September 1866 but on paper watermarked 1869 and in the violet ink first used in 1872. 1 p. 23 cm.
  - 18. NOTEBOOK (Box 32)
    Contains a few brief chronological notes on ancient history. Paper cover marked "Quarry". 26 p. 9 cm.
  - 19. NOTES, 1879 (Box 33)
    Criticism of Joseph Remi Léopold Delboeuf's article, "George-Henry Lewes. Sa vie et ses ouvrages" which appeared in La Revue Scientifique for 1 February 1879. 1 p. 15 cm.
    Sold at Sotheby's on 27 October 1959; gift of Gordon S. Haight and Richard L. Purdy in honor of Chauncey B. Tinker, 1959.
  - 20. DIARY, 1879 (Box 34)
    The original diary is in the Berg Collection of the New York Public Library, and permission to paraphrase or quote from this diary must be obtained from the Berg Collection. This typescript was prepared by R. H. Nims for Gordon S. Haight.
  - 21. [NOTEBOOK kept while studying Kant] (Box 35)
    Existence and Location of Originals
    Photocopy only, original at Nuneaton. This photocopy was made from a photocopy owned by Mrs. Joy Hooton, December 1984.
- Section V. George Eliot. WRITINGS. DRAMATIZATIONS.
  - 1. Program and review of Daniel Deronda dramatized by Lydia Lewisohn and Lily Tobias, "Q" Theatre, Kew, 14-20 February 1927. 2 pieces., 1927 Feb 14-20 (Box 36)
  - 2. Daniel Deronda, dramatized in 6 episodes for BBC by Alexander Baron, 1969. Recorded 14 June-4 August 1969; transmitted 11 April-13 May 1970. 365 leaves. (Box 36)
  - 3. Review of the first episode of Alexander Baron's dramatization of Daniel Deronda. Manuscript note on clipping: Telegraph 3-16-70. (Box 36)
- Section VI. George Henry Lewes. WRITINGS, 1856 Jul 24-1859 Mar 31
  - 1. JOURNAL X, 1856 Jul 24-1859 Mar 31 (Box 37)
  - 2. JOURNAL XI, 1859 Apr 1-1866 Jan 1 (Box 38)
  - 3. JOURNAL XII, 1866 Jun 1-1870 May 6 (Box 39)
  - 4. DIARY, 1869 (Box 40)
  - 5. DIARY, 1870 (Box 41)
  - 6. DIARY, 1871 (Box 42)
  - 7. DIARY, 1872 (Box 43)
  - 8. DIARY, 1873 (Box 44)
  - 9. DIARY, 1874 (Box 45)
  - 10. DIARY, 1875 (Box 46)
  - 11. DIARY, 1876 (Box 47)
  - 11a. DIARY, 1877 (Box 48)
  - 12. NOTEBOOK, 1857 Feb (Box 49)
    Miscellaneous notes, quotations, sketches. 144 p. Written mostly in pencil.
  - 13. NOTEBOOK, [1860 Mar-1867] (Box 50)
    Miscellaneous notes, addresses, diary entries in Antwerp and Holland. 148 p. Written mostly in pencil.
  - 14. NOTEBOOK (Box 51)
    Miscellaneous notes, addresses, quotations about Shakespeare, Pythagoras, etc. Several entries in ink. 110 p.
  - 15. "Extracts made by G.H. Lewes (Interesting)" (Box 52)
    127 p. (46 blank). "The Oedipus Colonos of Sophocles. Translated by G.H.L. 1843 (Sept -)" 16 p. at end.
  - 16. "Ariadne: or The Principles of Success and Failure in Literature.", 1861 (Box 53)
    Notebook, 66 leaves (4 blank). Published as "The Principles of Success and Failure in Literature" in the Fortnightly Review vol. 1-2, 1865.
  - 17. "Psychological Cases...Begun Dec 1866." (Box 53)
    58 leaves (48 blank). Probably miscellaneous notes for his Problems of Life and Mind.
  - 18. "Notes (Physiological)... Begun Feb 1873." (Box 54)
    138 leaves (86 blank). Probably miscellaneous notes for his Problems in Life and Mind.
  - 19. "Preparation for Hipparchus, Hipparchus, Ptolemy." (Box 55)
    47 leaves (15 blank).
  - 20. "Historical Note Books IV, V, VI centuries." (Box 55)
    48 leaves.
  - 21. "[Historical Note Books] VII & VIII cents. IX & X cents." (Box 55)
    49 - [94] leaves.
  - 22. "History dates, chronological summary." (Box 55)
    58 p. (11 blank).
  - 23. "Fragmentary M.S.S. of G. H. Lewes" (Box 55)
    some apparently for a Volume IV never published to be entitled 'The Study of Psychology"' Notes by GHL, GE, and others.
    Published as the third series of Problems of Life and Mind, 1879.
    Note: Larger portions of this manu- script are at Princeton, Huntington, and Berg.
    a. A list of 13 items beginning: George Eliot's copied notes from various notebooks of G. H. Lewes' philosophy." Miscellaneous notes on verso, one headed "Belief." l leaf.
    b. Table of contents in the hands of GHL and GE of the former's "The Study of Psychology, its object, scope, & method." 1 p.
    c. "Immediate & mediate knowledge." 7 p.
    d. "V. Laws of Matter in Mind." 24 leaves.
    e. Miscellaneous notes beginning with "Ruskin." 4 leaves.
    f. "Book II, Chap. I. The Alexandrian School." 24 leaves.
    g. "Notes on fragment of Parmenides printed in Lewes' Hist. Mat. pp. 54, 55." 3 leaves.
    h. "Remarks on Mr. Lewes' Chapters IV...VII." 16 p.
    i. "Being & existence are here treated as identical terms..." 24 p. numbered E to FF. Pencilled note on E: "Wm. Appleton?"
  - 24. "Drat that Dick! A Philosophical Farce. (Box 55)
    By Slingsby Lawrence Esq." 38 leaves.
  - 25. "The Fox who got the Grapes. A comedy in One Act." 42 leaves. Note on cover: "Turned into 'Mrs. Beauchamp's Vengeance' in Blackwood." (Box 55)
  - 26. "Glimpses & Guesses" 18 p. (Box 55)
    "Thoughts of G.H. Lewes", cover title in Mrs. Ouvry's hand.
  - 27. "Goethe.", [1854-55?] (Box 55)
    22 leaves
  - 28. "Marguerite." (Box 55)
    A play in 5 acts. 47 leaves.
  - 29. "The Miser's niece. Comedy in 2 Acts." (Box 55)
    29 leaves.
  - 30. "Pretension; or The School for (Box 55)
    Parvenus. A Comedy in 5 Acts." 85 leaves.
  - 31. [The Nervous Mechanism]. (Box 56)
    Possibly the first draft of the chapter on this subject in the second series of The Problems of Life and Mind. 21 leaves numbered 166-[177].
  - 32. PROBLEMS OF LIFE AND MIND. (Box 56)
    Part of Vol. III, Part I, etc. in folder labelled "Colour, Sensation." 103 p.
  - 33. PROBLEMS OF LIFE AND MIND. (Box 56)
    Part of vol. IV, in George Eliot's hand. 6 leaves.
  - 34. PROBLEMS OF LIFE AND MIND. (Box 56)
    Chapters XI-XIV of Problem III: "The Sphere of Sense and Logic of Feeling." (Third series). 69 leaves.
  - 35. PROBLEMS OF LIFE AND MIND. (Box 56)
    Chapter on "Belief." 9 leaves.
  - 36. PROBLEMS OF LIFE AND MIND? (Box 56)
    Notes on "Insanity" (in folder marked "Hallucinations") probably intended for another volume of Problems of Life and Mind. 24 leaves.
  - 37. PROBLEMS OF LIFE AND MIND (Box 56)
    Chapter on "Intuition." 5 leaves.
  - 38. PROBLEMS OF LIFE AND MIND. (Box 56)
    Appendix B of vol. II: "Lagrange and Hegel: The Speculative Method." 28 leaves numbered 257-284.
  - 39. "Thoughts for the Thoughtful. (Box 56)
    Part III."
  - 40. Notes of requirements for examination in classical languages, history, geography, logic, and political philosophy. 1 p., [c. 1865] (Box 56)
  - 41. SAVELLO, [1871] (Box 56)
    GHL's sketch of a tragedy in 3 acts adapted from Carl Dietrich Ludwig Felix von Rumohr, "Der letzte Savello," published in Urania. Taschenbuch auf das Jahr 1834, Leipzig, 1834 and re- printed in Deutscher Novellenschatz, ed. P. Heyse and H. Kurz, Munich, II (1871), 125-209. The Savello-Cassandra episode is found in pp. 184-209. Written in pencil by GHL and traced over by GE in ink. GHL mentions reading the story in his Diary, 2 August 1871.
  - "Notes and additions to the Theologico- Political Tractate" of Spinoza: notes accompanying GE's translation of Spinoza's Ethics. (Box 56)
    FILED WITH IV. 11.
- Section VII. George Eliot. ASSOCIATION ITEMS
  - 1. THE LINNET'S LIFE, London 1822. (Box 56)
    The first book GE received from her father. Inscribed on flyleaf [1870?] and presented to J. W. Cross in 1880.
  - 2. George Eliot. (Box 56)
    Agatha, London, 1869, and How Lisa Loved the King, Boston, 1869, bound together with an inscription to Mrs. William Cross, January, 1874. Additions and corrections in GE's hand on pages 10, 16, 18, 24, 34, 37, 47, and pencil markings for reading aloud.
  - 3. Thomas à Kempis' De Imitatione Christi, 1853. (Box 56)
    Presented by GE to John Walter Cross on their wedding day. Inscribed by Cross "JWC from MAC 6 May 1880".
  - 4. John Walter Cross. (Box 56)
    A notebook with M. E. L. stamped on cover contains one note (the address of Josiah Mills, coal merchant, now almost obliterated) in GE's hand and several by J. W. Cross, soon after her death, chiefly dates drawn probably from her journals.
- Section VIII. George Eliot. WRITINGS ABOUT.
  - 1. List of GE's manuscripts made by (Box 57)
    Charles Lee Lewes, probably in 1880, with a note by Mrs. Ouvry: "Most of these sold 1923 at Sotheby." 3 p. 18 cm.
  - 2. Reviews of GE's works.
    - a. SCENES OF CLERICAL LIFE, 1858
      - Saturday Review, p. 566-567., 1858 May 29 (Box 57)
      - Saturday Review, p. 583-584., 1858 Jun 5 (Box 57)
    - b. ADAM BEDE, 1859
      - Athenaeum, p. 284., 1859 Feb 26 (Box 57)
      - Bentley's Quarterly Review, 1, p. 433-456., 1859 (Box 57)
      - Literary Gazette, p. 281-283., 1859 Feb 26 (Box 57)
      - Saturday Review, p. 250-251., 1859 Feb 26 (Box 57)
      - Westminster Review, 71, p. 486-512., 1859 Apr (Box 57)
      - Emile Montégut, "Le roman réaliste en Angleterre" in Revue des deux mondes, II 21, p. 867-897 [p. 867- 894 missing)., 1859 Jun 15 (Box 57)
    - c. THE MILL ON THE FLOSS, 1860
      - The Times, [E. S. Dallas], 1860 May 19 (Box 57)
    - d. THE SPANISH GYPSY, 1868
      - Macmillan's Magazine, 18, p. 281-287., 1868 (Box 57)
    - e. MIDDLEMARCH, 1873
      - Quarterly Review, 134, p. 336-369., 1873 (Box 57)
      - St. Paul's Magazine, 12, p. 592-616., 1873 (Box 57)
    - f. DANIEL DERONDA, 1876
      - Wilhelm Scherer in Deutsche Rundschau, 10, p. 240-255., 1877 (Box 57)
      - R. E. Francillon in Gentleman's Magazine, 17, p. 410-427., 1876 (Box 57)
      - J. Jacobs in Macmillan's Magazine, 36, p. 101-111., 1877 (Box 57)
      - E. P. Whipple in North American Review, 124, p. 31-52., 1877 (Box 57)
      - Unidentified, headed "Literature of the Day," p. 645-648., 1876 (Box 57)
    - g. General reviews:
      - National Review, 11, p. 191-219., 1860 (Box 57)
      - Standard., [June 1876?] (Box 57)
      - J. Morley, Macmillan's Magazine, 14, p. 272-279., 1866 (Box 57)
      - James Sully, Mind, 6, p. 378-394., 1881 (Box 57)
      - Edward Dowden, Contemporary Review, 20, p. 403-422., 1872 (Box 57)
      - Edward Dowden, Contemporary Review, 29, p. 348-369., 1877 (Box 57)
      - Miss C. H. Spence, Melbourne Review p. [146]-163., 1876 Apr (Box 57)
      - Unidentified. "Realistic Novelists," p. 200-224. (Box 57)
  - 3. Blackwood, Wm. & Sons.
    Estimates of the cost of publishing GE's works:
    See: correspondence with Wm. Blackwood & Sons.
    - Scenes from Clerical Life, [1859] (Box 57)
    - Adam Bede, Mill on the Floss, Silas Marner, Felix Holt., 1866 (Box 57)
    - Middlemarch, 1872-73 (Box 57)
    - Cabinet Edition of Works, 2 pieces., n.d. (Box 57)
    - Cheap Edition of 5 novels., n.d. (Box 57)
  - 4. Blackwood, Wm. & Sons.
    - Statement of sales of GE's works 23 pieces., 1861-1885 (Box 57)
      Tinker 959
  - 5. Memoranda of stocks and bonds.
    - a. Register of Investments: autograph list by John Walter Cross with a few entries by GE and later entries by Cross. 90 p. 21 cm., 1879 Mar (Box 57)
    - b. "Schedule of Stock & Share Certificates belonging to Mrs. Lewes," with marginal notes by GE. 1 p. 33 cm., 1878 May 1 (Box 57)
    - c. "Memorandum of Property deposited with The Union Bank of London Charing Cross Branch in the name of Mrs. M. E. Lewes." 1 p. 34 cm., 1880 Apr 24 (Box 57)
    - d. "To the Holders of India £4 per- Cent Stock...": printed notice, endorsed by C. L. Lewes: "Mrs. Müllers Trust" [probably Mrs. Eduard Müller, wife of the headmaster of Hofwyl School]., 1887 Apr 19 (Box 57)
  - 6. Certified copy of the record of GE's baptism, 29 April 1819. Signed by G. R. Pennington, Chilvers Coton, 30 April 1881. 1 p. (Box 57)
  - 7. Deed of declaration adopting the surname of Lewes in addition to the name of Evans. Signed Mary Ann Evans and witnessed by Charles Lee Lewes, with envelope addressed by GE. 2 p. 33 cm., 1879 Jan 31 (Box 57)
  - 8. Photocopies of extracts from the settlement by GE on her marriage to J. W. Cross and from her will, pre- pared by Duncan, Warren and Gardner, solicitors, 8 p. 32 cm., 1880 May 4-1881 Feb 9 (Box 57)
  - 9. Photocopy of the announcement in The Times of GE's marriage to J. W. Cross. 1 card. 10.5 cm., 1880 May 8 (Box 57)
  - 10. London Cemetery Company.
    - Receipt for GE's burial charges, paid by J. W. Cross, 1880 Dec 27 (Box 57)
    - Account of GE's funeral, from The Times., 1880 Dec 30 (Box 57)
  - 11. Agreement between Mrs. Elinor Ouvry and Mary Margaret Paterson about George Eliot's Family Life and Letters by Arthur Henry Paterson. 2 p., 1928 Feb 14 (Box 57)
  - 12. Letters to Ernest Carrington Ouvry about Arthur Paterson's George Eliot's Family Life and Letters from:
    - a. The Author's Syndicate, signed by Margaret Sanders., 1930 Jan 30 (Box 57)
    - b. William Archibald Spooner, 1844-1930., 1928 Apr 10 (Box 57)
    - c. Ernest Barker., 1928 Apr 18 (Box 57)
    - d. Lord Bertie of Thame., 1928 Apr 23 (Box 57)
  - 13. Reviews of Arthur Henry Paterson's George Eliot's Family Life and Letters mounted in red notebook., 1928 (Box 57)
  - 14. The Spectator., 1932 Jul 23-Sep 17
    Clippings of correspondence about GE and the Lewes family by:
    Manuscript letters relating to the correspondence in The Spectator:
    - Adamson, Mary M., p. 111, Jul 23 (Box 57)
    - Matthews, Hubert B. (Box 57)
    - Gardner, Charles (Box 57)
    - Matthews, Hubert B., p. 155, Jul 30 (Box 57)
    - Church, Richard (Box 57)
    - G.M., p. 234, Aug 20 (Box 57)
    - Ouvry, Elinor Southwood (Lewes) p. 344, Sep 17 (Box 57)
    - Adamson, Mary M., 1932 Jul 30 (Box 57)
    - ALS to Mrs. Ouvry. (Box 57)
    - Ouvry, Elinor., 1932 Aug (Box 57)
    - Draft of a letter to Mary M. Adamson. (Box 57)
    - Adamson, Mary M., 1932 Sep 18 (Box 57)
    - ALS to Mrs. Ouvry. (Box 57)
    - Buxton, Violet., 1932 Sep 18 (Box 57)
    - ALS to Mrs. Ouvry. (Box 57)
  - 15. Paris, Bernard J. "George Eliot's Unpublished Poetry" [a study of Eliot IV.7] reprinted from Studies in Philology, LVI, 3, July 1959. 3 copies. (Box 57)
  - 16. Taylor, Don. "The Confessions of Marian Evans. A Portrait of George Eliot.", 1969 Nov 23 (Box 57)
    Typescript of the dramatization pre- sented on BBC television. 63 p.
  - 17. Currey, Stella Martin. "Scenes from an Improper Life.", 1972 Apr 19-29 (Box 57)
    Program for the dramatization pre- sented at Leamington Theatre, April 19-22, 24-29, 1972.
  - 18. Questions about the original manuscript of Middlemarch. (Box 57)
  - 19. "A Hundred Years after 'Middlemarch.' (Box 57)
    Offering the corrected proofs of the works of George Eliot from the Archives of the Publishers William Blackwood and Sons, Ltd. 1857-1880." Catalogue of Lew David Feldman, House of El Dieff, Inc.
  - 20. Haight, Gordon S. (Box 57)
    George Eliot. A Biography. Author's corrected typescript and proof sheets of the biography published by the Oxford University Press in 1968.
    Gift of Gordon S. Haight, 1974.
  - 21. Tee, G.J., 1976-77 (Box 60)
    "Sof'ya Vasil'yevna Kovalevskaya". Offprint from Mathematical Chronicle, v.5, 1976-77. Gift of the author.
  - 22. Miscellaneous articles about GE (Box 60)
    7 items.
  - 23. Payne, John Burnell (Box 60)
    Typescript of his notes of a conver- sation with George Eliot.
- Section IX. George Eliot. SPECIAL FILES
  - 1. Blank writing paper of GE (Box 61)
    The Priory, 21 North Bank, Regents Park. 3 sheets, folded. The Heights, Witley, nr. Godalming. 1 half-sheet. 1 plain envelope.
  - 2. Calling card of Mr. & Mrs. Cross (Box 61)
    The Heights, Witley.
  - 3. Photograph of GE's blotter, with extracts from various authors, notes for poems, etc., mounted in a folder. (Box 61)
    26 cm. Three smaller pieces of genuine GE blotting paper laid in. 19 cm.
  - 4. Photographs of GE or said to be of GE
    - a. Originals in the National Portrait Gallery: (Box 61)
    - b. Glass negative of D'Albert Durade's portrait of GE, made by Howard A. Kelly. (Box 61)
    - c. Photograph of a painting by Sophus Williams. (Box 61)
    - d. Photograph of GE made by the London Stereoscopic and Photographic Company, 2 copies. (Box 61)
    - No. 669 Chalk drawing by F. W. Burton. 5 copies., 1865 (Box 61)
    - No. 1232 Watercolor by Mrs. C. Bray. 2 copies., 1842 (Box 61)
    - No. 1405 Copy of a portrait by F. D'Albert Durade, the original of which is in the Gulson Library, Coventry., 1849 (Box 61)
    - No. 1758 Pencil sketch by Lady Alma-Tadema., 1877 (Box 61)
    - No. 2210 Drawing by Margaret Gillies? (Box 61)
    - No. 2211 Pencil sketch by Lady Alma-Tadema., n.d. (Box 61)
    - No. 2645 Silhouette, artist unknown. Not GE, n.d. (Box 61)
    - e. Photograph of pencil sketch by GE made by Princess Louise. The original in the possession of Mrs. Reginald Allen, New York City., 1879 Mar 16 (Box 61)
    - f. Photograph of a chalk drawing of GE by Samuel Laurence., 1860 (Box 61)
    - g. J. W. Cross's framed copy of Rajon's etching from the 1858 photograph. (Box 61)
    - h. Profile, with lace head-covering. (Box 61)
    - i. Full face, with hood. Not GE. (Box 61)
    - j. Two pencil sketches of GE by Barbara Bodichon pasted on flyleaves of Romola., 1877 (Box 62)
  - 5. Photographs of GE's homes
    - a. Doorway of Griff House, Chilvers Coton. (Box 63)
    - b. Brookbank, Shottermill. (Box 63)
    - c. Witley, The Heights. (Box 63)
  - 6. Poems written to or sent to GE